<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A short view of the chief points in controversy between the reformed churches and the Church of Rome in two letters to the Duke of Bouillon, upon his turning papist / written by the Reverend Peter Du Moulin ...</title>
            <author>Du Moulin, Pierre, 1568-1658.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 106 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 48 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A36881</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D2596</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R17193</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13646501</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13646501</idno>
            <idno type="VID">100925</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A36881)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 100925)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 786:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A short view of the chief points in controversy between the reformed churches and the Church of Rome in two letters to the Duke of Bouillon, upon his turning papist / written by the Reverend Peter Du Moulin ...</title>
                  <author>Du Moulin, Pierre, 1568-1658.</author>
                  <author>Du Moulin, Peter, 1601-1684.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 88 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Benjamin Tooke ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1680.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Newly translated out of French copy which was never printed."</note>
                  <note>Letters written by Pierre Du Moulin fifty years earlier.  Cf. pref.</note>
                  <note>Edited by Peter Du Moulin the Younger.  Cf. BM.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:100925:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:100925:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SHORT VIEW OF THE Chief Points IN CONTROVERSY Between the REFORMED CHURCHES And the CHURCH of <hi>ROME.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>IN Two LETTERS to the Duke of <hi>Bouillon,</hi> upon his turning PAPIST.</p>
            <p>Written by the Reverend <hi>PETER D<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g> MO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LIN,</hi> Profeſſor of Divinity in the Univerſity of <hi>Sedan.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Newly tranſlated out of the</hi> FRENCH <hi>Copy, which was never Printed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Benjamin Tooke,</hi> at the Ship in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-Yard 1680.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:100925:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:100925:2"/>
            <head>To the Honourable Sir <hi>NORTON KNATCHB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>L,</hi> Knight and Baronet.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Honourable Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THeſe Letters written fifty years ago to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the Duke of <hi>Bouillon</hi> to the Proteſtant Religion which he had forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, never were put to the Preſs, for Fear of provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king that great Lord to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute them with Arguments of Power, againſt which thoſe of Truth and Learning too of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
<pb facs="tcp:100925:3"/>cannot ſtand. That they now come out in <hi>Engliſh,</hi> the Church of <hi>England</hi> is obliged, Sir, to you, who ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving by your diligent Search made your ſelf Owner of a fair Manuſcript of the ſame, were pleaſed to beſtow it upon me, the Authors Son; ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding your Requeſt, which to me is a Command, that I would tranſlate it into <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh,</hi> and give it to the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick. I have now obeyed your Order, which I could not have done in a more ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable Conjuncture, and I cannot in Duty but return
<pb facs="tcp:100925:3"/>this Tranſlation to the bounti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Giver of the Original. Sir, you have by your excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Labours already publiſht, ſhewn to the World how well you can match hearty Piety with eminent Learning. Now you are pleaſed to give ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Inſtance of your Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to both, by procuring the ſetting forth theſe following Treatiſes. Short indeed they are, but as compact with the Sinews of Reaſon and Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as any that ever came from the Study of that ſtrong Champion of Gods Cauſe. May God be glorified by it, his
<pb facs="tcp:100925:4"/>Truth aſſerted, his Oppoſers converted, and your Zeal for Gods Truth and Glory be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded by God, and imitated by men. So prayeth</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>SIR,</salute> 
               <signed>Your true Honourer, and moſt humble Servant. PETER DU MOULIN.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:100925:4"/>
            <head>THE FIRST EPISTLE.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MY LORD,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>UPON hearing the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port that you purpoſe to change your Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I continued a long time doubtful whether I ſhould write to Your Grace about it. For, being hardly perſwaded that ſuch a thought could come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your mind, I was afraid to be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſive to Your Grace by my Miſtruſt. But now, ſeeing that Report to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue and increaſe, I could hold no longer from imparting my thoughts to Your Grace upon that Subject, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing inferiour to none in Fidelity and Affection to your Service.</p>
            <p>You were inſtructed, My Lord, from your Infancy, by an Excellent Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and a Virtuous Mother, in a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:100925:5"/>of which you have learned to fear God, and ſerve him according to his Word. In that Religion, if you had met with ſome Scruple, you ought, at the leaſt, to have heard both the Parties, and not have taken counſel onely of the Adverſaries. This is plain tempting of God, who being thereby juſtly provoked, blindeth the Spirit of thoſe that ſeek occaſions to turn from his Service.</p>
            <p>Had Your Grace done me that Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to acquaint me with your Doubts, I might have eaſily ſhewed you, that the <hi>Roman</hi> Religion is altogether con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Word of God. That they celebrate every day a propitiatory Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice for the Redemption of Souls, other than the Death of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt. That the Communion of the Cup, expreſly commanded in Scripture, is denied to the Laity. That the People ſay Prayers to God which they do not underſtand, and the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Service is performed in a Language unknown to them, contrary to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs Prohibition of the Apoſtle.<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.16.</note> That the Trinity is repreſented in carved Stone and Picture, and the Adoration of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:100925:5"/>Images is enjoyned by many Popes and new Councels, contrary to Gods expreſs Prohibition in the Second Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; Which was taken away from the Law of God in the Offices and Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viaries, that the People might not ſee it. That Bones and Relicks of Saints are adored. That by the Doctrine of their Purgatory God is made to burn the Souls of his Children for Sins fully pardoned, and for which Jeſus Chriſt hath wholly ſatisfied, and that not to mend the Sinners, but to ſatisfie his Juſtice. That the Pope, without any Authority from the Word of God, taketh upon him to be Succeſſor to St. <hi>Peter</hi> in the Apoſtleſhip, and in the Primacy over the Univerſal Church. To defend which Primacy, Epiſtles and Decretals of the Antient Biſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> were forged, and many Books and ſuppoſititious Paſſages, the falſhood whereof we ſhew by invincible Proofs.</p>
            <p>In Decrees, Councels, Canons, and Principal Authors of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, the Pope is called God, and the Divine Majeſty, having all Power in Heaven and Earth: By which Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:100925:6"/>he fetcheth Souls out of Purgatory, puts ſuch as he pleaſeth in the Liſt of the Saints by Canonizing them, giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Pardons of Sins of two or three thouſand years, giveth and taketh away Kingdoms, diſpenſeth with Oaths made unto God, diſſolveth Marriages lawfully contracted, boaſting that he cannot err in the Faith, and that he hath Power to add new Articles to the Creed, to be Judge above Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, and to alter that which God hath inſtituted in his Word. Of theſe I could bring to Your Grace a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Proofs, drawn from the Decrees and Councels of Popes, and from Publick Experience.</p>
            <p>The Pope boaſteth that he hath a Treaſure in which he layeth up all the Overplus of the Penitential Works of the Saints, and diſtributeth them unto others by his Indulgences, and makes multitudes to travel two or three hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Leagues to get the Remiſſion of their Sins, which is offered to them at home <hi>gratis</hi> by the Doctrine of the Goſpel. If a Rich man dieth, who hath given any thing to the Church, he hath many private Maſſes, Obits,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:100925:6"/>and Suffrages for his Money. But ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver any private Maſs is ſung for a Beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, or one that hath given nothing.</p>
            <p>In the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, departed Saints are prayed to, of whom Holy Scripture ſaith, that they know not the Hearts of men, and whoſe Invoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion hath neither Command nor Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, nor Promiſe in the Word of God.</p>
            <p>I am told that Your Grace hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ear to <hi>Capucins,</hi> who have for their Patron and Author of their Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der St. <hi>Francis;</hi> whoſe Life, if you had read, as our Adverſaries themſelves have publiſh'd it, you might think that it was purpoſely written to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fame him. There you may find how he preach'd unto Birds; that being ſtark naked, he embraced a Woman made of Snow to repreſs his Heats; that he took up again the Lice that fell down from his Garments, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny the like Feats. Theſe <hi>Capucins,</hi> as other <hi>Monks,</hi> boaſt that they doe Works of <hi>Supererogation,</hi> that is, bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and more perfect Works than God hath commanded in his Law; For which therefore they look for a
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:100925:7"/>degree of Glory in Paradiſe above other Saints, who had attained to no greater Perfection than to fulfil the Law of God perfectly, who thereby have not got any greater Reward than Eternal Life.</p>
            <p>If by the Doctrine of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church you are obliged to get Eternal Life by your Merits, inſtead of put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting your whole truſt in Gods Mercy, through Jeſus Chriſt, you ſhall never enjoy any Peace of Conſcience, ſeeing that the moſt righteous Perſons have great Defects, and ſtand in need of Gods Pardon. Good works indeed are neceſſary to Salvation, not from any merit in them, but as the onely means preſcribed by God to attain the the Kingdom of Heaven.</p>
            <p>One of the great Diſeaſes of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church is, that a Sinner, after he hath confeſs'd his Sins to a Prieſt, receiveth from him the Pardon of them: A Sinner forgiveth another Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner Offences committed againſt God; as if a Felon did forgive another Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon Crimes committed againſt the King. Thereby a man makes himſelf a Judge in Gods Cauſe. A Prieſt takes
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:100925:7"/>upon him to be Judge of Sins which he knoweth not, for he knoweth not the Thoughts and the Affections of the Heart, in which Sin doth chiefly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt. Neither doth he know the truth of the Sinners Repentance, without which there is no Pardon. Indeed faithful Paſtors have received of Chriſt the Power to remit Sins, as touching the Eccleſiaſtical Penalty and Cenſure of the Church, and to reconcile the Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner excluded from the Communion, to the Church: But you would be much diſappointed if you thought that the Pardon given you by a Prieſt doth exempt you from anſwering for your Actions before Gods Judgment Seat. For when the King forgives a Felon, he doth not exempt him from being judged by that great Judge.</p>
            <p>Can a man that feareth God, and to whom God hath left ſome liberty of Judgement, read without horrour the <hi>Cauteles</hi> and Rubricks of the Maſs in the beginning of the Miſſal which the Prieſt hath upon the Altar? Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by Proviſion is made againſt the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniencies that may happen to the Conſecrated Hoſt, when it happens
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:100925:8"/>that Mice have gnawn the Maſs-God, or when a Beaſt hath devoured it, or when the Wind hath carried it away, or when the Prieſt or a ſick perſon hath vomited it. Can ye find in your heart to worſhip a God that may be ſtollen, or eaten by Beaſts, or blown away by the Wind, and that being fallen cannot raiſe himſelf? How ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times doth Scripture ſay, That Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt gave Bread to his Diſciples, and that we break and eat Bread in the Lords Supper?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 22.19, 20.</note> That Bread is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Body of Chriſt, as it is in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of him. In the ſame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, as in the next line the Cup is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the New Teſtament, becauſe it is the Sign and the Memorial of it; There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Apoſtles did not worſhip it. The <hi>Roman</hi> Church holds that Jeſus Chriſt did communicate in the Holy Euchariſt with his Diſciples. All Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties agree that it follows from the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of that Church that Jeſus Chriſt did eat himſelf, and had his Head and his Feet in his Mouth. The Goſpel tells us, that in that Holy Action the Devil entred into <hi>Judas:</hi> Can ye believe that Jeſus Chriſt and the Devil entred to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether into him?</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:100925:8"/>
            <p>To ſtrengthen theſe Errours, the ſixth Chapter of St. <hi>Johns</hi> Goſpel is impertinently alleged, in which the Lord Jeſus ſpeaks of <hi>giving his Fleſh to eat;</hi> for Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> the III, and after him a multitude of Doctors have determined, that in that Chapter the Euchariſt is not meant at all, and that theſe words of <hi>giving his Fleſh to eat,</hi> muſt be underſtood of a Spiritual eating by Faith. There Jeſus Chriſt ſpeaks to the <hi>Capernaïtes,</hi> to whom he promiſeth to give his Fleſh for their meat, but he never gave them the Euchariſt. He ſpeaks to them of a manner of Eating neceſſary to Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and without which none can be ſaved, ſaying,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 6.53.</note> 
               <hi>Except ye eat the Fleſh of the Son of man there is no Life in you.</hi> Now many are ſaved without receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Euchariſt, as the converted Thief, crucified with Chriſt, and <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt, and many Martyrs. And Jeſus Chriſt declareth, that by Eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Drinking he underſtands Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving, when he ſaith,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>v.</hi> 35.</note> 
               <hi>He that cometh to me ſhall never hunger, and he that believeth on me ſhall never thirſt.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he warneth them,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>v.</hi> 63.</note> that <hi>the words
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:100925:9"/>which he ſaid unto them, were Spirit and Life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is acknowledged by all, that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Prieſts of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church are ill-Livers; yet it is the Doctrine of that Church, that a Prieſt, who hath been wallowing all Night in a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauch, hath the power in the Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to make a God with five words, and hath him in his power. I muſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo humbly beſeech your Grace to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, that the Councel of <hi>Trent</hi> decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth it to be the Tenet of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Church, generally believed, that Sacraments are Null if the Prieſt hath no Intention to Conſecrate; which In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention is preſumed but by Conjecture, and none can be certain of it, ſo that the People adore an Hoſt not knowing whether it be conſecrated, which is an Adoration at a venture. Neither can any in the <hi>Roman</hi> Church be certain whether he be baptized, for none knoweth the Intention of him that baptizeth, nor that of him that gave him Orders.</p>
            <p>Theſe things, my Lord, I touch ſummarily, of which the Proofs are eaſie, but too long for a Letter. To
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:100925:9"/>diſguiſe theſe Truths unto Your Grace; I am told, that you have been perſwaded to read the Invectives of <hi>Barklay,</hi> in which Scripture is hardly alledged; and <hi>Gualtiers</hi> Chronicle, which is but a web of falſe paſſages of ſome ſuppoſititious Books (which are not received by the Learned of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church) or Calumnies impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted unto us, and ſuch things as we never thought on.</p>
            <p>If, upon thoſe falſe Paſſages and Calumnies Your Grace had been plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to conſult with ſome of our Side, expert in ſuch Matters, they would have made you ſee evidently the falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood of them. The like I ſay of ſome paſſages of Fathers ſhewed unto Your Grace, moſt of them taken out of forged Writings, whoſe falſhood is acknowledged by our Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. We have Fathers only as they were copied out of Manuſcripts that were found in Monaſteries, written by <hi>Monks,</hi> who have falſified them, and whoſe falſe dealing is diſcovered by the diverſity of the Copies, of which I could ſhew you many Inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, if I had the Honour to converſe
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:100925:10"/>with Your Grace about that Subject. But God hath not permitted our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries to bring to an end that En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprize of corrupting all the Fathers; for numberleſs Paſſages are found in them which bear witneſs unto the Truth: For which the Doctors of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church blame them very often, and give them many ill words.</p>
            <p>But, becauſe that Diſcourſe might grow too to great a length, I do on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly refer Your Grace to a Paper by it ſelf a<note n="*" place="margin">Which die Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſhall find in the ſecond Chapter of this Authors Anatomy of the Maſs.</note> Compariſon of the Lords Supper with the Maſs, that you may know what horrible alteration was made in the Lords Inſtitution, and that you may know that by going to Maſs you cannot be ſaved. You (I ſay) My Lord, who have been favoured with ſo many Bleſſings of God, who have had an Holy and Vertuous Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, and have a thouſand Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to your Illuſtrious Lady Mother, whoſe days are likely now to be ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with anguiſh and ſorrow.</p>
            <p>God hath given to Your Grace in this City<note n="*" place="margin">Sedan.</note> a Faithful People, heartily devoted to your Service, which have built your Town, and fortified it with
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:100925:10"/>their hard Labour, and have not been ſparing of their Lives and means to defend this State when it was in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. They are a People whom God hath gathered from many places and ſheltered under your ſhadow, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting them to your keeping. The Subſiſtence of this little State of yours, compaſſed about with Mighty States, depends, next to God, upon the Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity of the Inhabitants, and their Love to their Sovereign. Think you what Heart-breaking Sorrow it will be to that poor People, when they ſee Your Grace going to Maſs. What Diſſipation, what Deſolation ſhall you ſee ere long in your City, when the Holy Scripture ſhall be baniſh'd from your Houſe? when, inſtead of the pure Service of God, the Service of Images ſhall be eſtabliſhed, Beads, <hi>Agnus Dei's,</hi> and ſprinklings of Holy Water? When, inſtead of a Few Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors, you ſhall have Herds of Fryars ſowing Diſcord continually among your Subjects? When Eccleſiaſtical Goods ſhall be no more in your diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, and the <hi>Roman</hi> Clergy muſt have again that which your Predeceſſors had
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:100925:11"/>juſtly taken from them, whereby your Revenues ſhall ſuffer a great Diminu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? When all the Eccleſiaſtical and Matrimonial Cauſes ſhall be no more under the Juriſdiction of your Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, but muſt be tried at <hi>Chalons</hi> or <hi>Rheims,</hi> ſo that you ſhall be no more Maſter at home? When inſtead of Subjects, altogether depending upon your Authority, you ſhall have <hi>Jeſuits</hi> and <hi>Capucins</hi> about you, having a ſtrict Intelligence with thoſe of <hi>Brux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els,</hi> whence Jealouſies and Fears will ariſe greatly noiſome to your State.</p>
            <p>I could repreſent to Your Grace many Conſiderations to make you ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend that by this Action you will ruin your Affairs, even in this World, and loſe the Love of thoſe that have been your principal Honour and Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, that hereby you will pull up the roots of your Reputation, Honour and Greatneſs, fill with Grief and Confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on your deareſt Relations, and draw upon you the Contempt of Perſons of both Religions. For even the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt men of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church in <hi>France,</hi> that govern themſelves by Humane Prudence, ſay, that you take your
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:100925:11"/>Meaſures amiſs, and cannot believe that ever you will take that Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution.</p>
            <p>But the worſt conſequence of it is, that thereby you will loſe your Soul. For you have a great Account to give unto God, who knoweth the Hearts, who is juſt and terrible, and will not dally with thoſe that dally with him. I have poured forth, and pour ſtill for your Grace Prayers before God, &amp; Sighs without number; neither am I with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out hope that God will be merciful unto you. One thing at leaſt, My Lord, let me crave at your hands, that if you have any Scruples &amp; Doubts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout your Religion, you will be pleaſed to defer your final Reſolution, till be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing come to this Town, you may hear the two Parties, and till we may ſpeak to ſome Doctors of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church in your Preſence. And I may be bold to promiſe to Your Grace to make you acknowledge that you have been poſſeſs'd with Calumnies againſt us, that both the Tenets of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, and Ours, have been miſ-re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented to Your Grace, and that <hi>Gaultiers</hi> Paſſages are falſe and forged.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:100925:12"/>This, if I cannot obtain of Your Grace by my moſt humble Requeſt, yet ſo much comfort at leaſt I ſhall have, that I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ave diſcharged my Conſcience. But if I be ſo unfortunate as to loſe your Grace's Favour for ſpeaking the truth to you; it will be well for me that I have but few days to live in this World, which I will paſs away in ſorrow, tho' in hope to have them ended by Death, when it ſhall pleaſe God to receive me into his reſt. And what Sorrow ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver may exerciſe me in my Life, I will never leave praying for your Proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and Salvation, as reſolved to be as long as I live,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute> 
               <signed>Your Grace's moſt humble, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:100925:12"/>
            <head>A SECOND LETTER OF Dr. <hi>DV MOVLIN</hi> TO THE DUKE of <hi>BOVILLON,</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">In Anſwer to a Letter of the Duke's to his Siſter <hi>Mademoiſelle de Bouillon.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MY LORD,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>MAdemoiſelle de Bouillon,</hi> your Siſter, hath done me the Honour to impart unto me Your Grace's Letters to her about the Cauſes that diſquiet your Conſcience. Upon which, I hope that your Goodneſs will not take it ill that I make ſome Reflections, and try whether God will make Uſe of me to contribute ſomething towards the Qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et of your Soul, and to turn you from
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:100925:13"/>the way which I ſee you take, contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the Doctrine of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>You begin, by expreſſing your De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign not to ſeparate your ſelf from my Lady Dutcheſs your Wife neither in this World nor in the other: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by you declare, that you had reſolved to be of your Ladies Religion, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you knew whether it was good or evil, and that your Enquiries about Matters of Religion were made after you had formed that Deſign, and taken that Reſolution. Concerning which I could ſay many things, but Reſpect ſtops me, being unwilling to be offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive to Your Grace.</p>
            <p>You ſay next, that you have not ſought the Grounds of the Religion of My Lady Dutcheſs any where but in the Holy Scripture. And yet in your whole Letter you allegde not any one Text of it.</p>
            <p>You ſay next, that it is a point in controverſie which are the Holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures; in which Queſtion we have great Advantages: For the Books of <hi>Tobit, Judith, Maccabees, &amp;c.</hi> are Books not extant in the <hi>Hebrew,</hi> which is the Original Tongue of the Scriptures
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:100925:13"/>of the <hi>Old Teſtament.</hi> Jeſus Chriſt and his Apoſtles cite the Books of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> the <hi>Pſalms,</hi> the <hi>Prophets, &amp;c.</hi> but never cite any of thoſe <hi>Apocryphal</hi> Books. The Jewiſh Church before Chriſts coming never did acknowledge thoſe Books<note n="*" place="margin">As we learn of <hi>Joſephus</hi> and <hi>Philo.</hi>
               </note>. And thoſe Books are ſtuffed with Fables, as I have fully ſhewed in my Book againſt Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal <hi>du Perron.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Book</hi> 1. <hi>chap.</hi> 61.</note> And whereas you ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal for the grounds of your Religion to the Fathers, we have for us the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel of <hi>Laodicea, Melito, Origen, Euſebi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, Athanaſius, Cyril</hi> of <hi>Jeruſalem, Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory Nazianzen, Amphilochius, Epipha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius, Tertullian, Hierom, Ruffin, Hila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, Philaſtrius, Gregory</hi> I. Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> and many more, all which to alledge might be tedious to your Grace: Yet, if you ſhall command it, I will ſend you a full Liſt of them.</p>
            <p>St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> in this Point doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict himſelf; and the Third Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of <hi>Carthage,</hi> which is objected to us, is otherwiſe in the <hi>Greek</hi> Copies than in the <hi>Latin.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:100925:14"/>
               <head>Of the Interpretation of Scripture.</head>
               <p>You add, that there is a Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie about the Interpretation of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. The Pope and the <hi>Roman</hi> Church boaſt themſelves to be the infallible In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreters, and Sovereign Judges of the Senſe of it. Yet the <hi>Roman</hi> Church never made any Interpretation of Scripture which was generally approved. We have onely Comments of Doctors, who diſagree among themſelves. Truly the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> intends not to make Scripture plainly underſtood, ſince ſhe hides it from the People, and will not have it to be read, and hath forbidden the Tranſlation of it into the vulgar Tongues. What Interpretati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on can we expect from the Pope, who boaſteth that he can change the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments of God, and ſaith that Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is ſubject unto him?</p>
               <p>Be pleaſed my Lord, eſpecially to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, whether it be juſt and reaſonable that the Pope ſhould be Judge in his own Cauſe, and whether the <hi>Roman</hi> Church can be the Sovereign Judge of her own Duty; and whether in this
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:100925:14"/>Queſtion, whether the <hi>Roman</hi> Church be a Sovereign Judge in points of Faith, the <hi>Roman</hi> Church her Self can be the Judge.</p>
               <p>To give you ſome Inſtances of this, Jeſus Chriſt ſaith to St. <hi>Peter,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.18.19.</note> and to all his Apoſtles, <hi>Whatſoever thou ſhalt bind on Earth, ſhall be bound in Heaven</hi> &amp;c. Upon which Text the <hi>Roman</hi> Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late groundeth his Primacy. In Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is it juſt, that he ſhould be acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged the Sovereign and infallible Judge and Interpreter of thoſe Texts upon which he groundeth his Empire? For who can doubt but that he will give Judgment on his own ſide; as indeed by his Interpretations he hath laid up for himſelf greater Riches than that of the greateſt Kings, and hath built to himſelf an earthly Empire. See then how he interprets that Text. Becauſe Chriſt hath ſaid, <hi>Whatſoever thou ſhalt looſe on Earth;</hi> the Pope pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends he may alſo looſe thoſe under the Earth, drawing Souls out of Purgato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. And whereas Jeſus Chriſt in that Text ſpeaks only of looſing Sinners, that are bound with Eccleſiaſtical Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, the Pope from that Text aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumes
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:100925:15"/>unto himſelf the Power of loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Subjects from the Obedience ſworn unto their Princes, of diſpenſing with Oaths, of freeing Children from the Obedience due to their Fathers, and of diſſolving Marriages lawfully con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted. And whereas Chriſt gave to all his Diſciples that looſing Power, the Pope hath reſerved unto himſelf many Caſes, in which none but him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf can give Abſolution. Beſides, he ſo interpreteth that Text, as if all that is ſaid unto St. <hi>Peter</hi> was ſaid unto the Pope, of which yet the Scripture ſaith nothing, and giveth to St. <hi>Peter</hi> no Succeſſor in his Primacy or in his Apoſtleſhip.</p>
               <p>Your ſelf, My Lord, may judge whether the Pope, who hath forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Marriage unto Biſhops, can be a good Interpreter of the words of the Apoſtle,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.2, 3.</note>, <hi>A Biſhop muſt be the Husband of one Wife, having his children ſubject in all gravity.</hi> Whether the Pope ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving taken away the Cup of the Lords Supper from the Laity, can be a good Interpreter of theſe words of Chriſt, <hi>Drink ye all of it.</hi> Whether the Pope and the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, which by Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:100925:15"/>of Councels command the Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of Images, can be good Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preters of the Second Commandement which forbids it. Whether the Pope, who makes Ordinances for publick Brothel-houſes at <hi>Rome,</hi> can be a good Interpreter of Gods Commandement, <hi>Thou ſhalt not commit Adultery.</hi> Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Pope, who forbids Fleſh and other Meats, can be a good Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the Apoſtles Precept, <hi>Whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver is ſet before you, eat, asking no que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion for Conſcience ſake.</hi> Whether the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, which in the Councel of <hi>Trent</hi> defineth, that <hi>Coveting</hi> is no ſin, be a good Interpreter of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, <hi>Thou ſhalt not covet.</hi> Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Pope, who brings into the publick Service a Language not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood by the People, can be a good Interpreter of the fourteenth Chapter of the firſt Epiſtle to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> where it is ſo many times forbidden to pray and ſpeak in the Church in an unknown Tongue. Whether Pope <hi>John</hi> XXIII, who denied the Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality of the Soul, and for that Crime and many more was condemned by the Councel of <hi>Conſtance,</hi> could have
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:100925:16"/>been a good Interpreter of thoſe Texts of Scripture which ſpeak of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Life.</p>
               <p>For your part, My Lord, you take another courſe. For, without ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Authority of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, which acknowledgeth no Judge but the Pope, you ſay that you have found in the Fathers of the five firſt Centuries, the Religion which you ſeem reſolved to embrace. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you reſiſt openly the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, which admitteth not the Fathers for her Judges, and condemn them ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry often of Errour, Ignorance, and He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie.</p>
               <p>Then you contradict the very Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, who in a thouſand places refuſe to be believed or received for Judges, and ſend the Reader continually to the Holy Scripture. Hardly ſhall you find many Texts of Scripture wherein the Fathers agree about the Interpretation. You may be pleaſed therefore to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, that you undertake a Journey in a way where you ſee no Light. They are <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Latin</hi> Fathers which you never read, and where you can get no Information for your
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:100925:16"/>Judgment. A man that hath nothing elſe to do, needs to ſpend ten years in ſtudy before he can get ſome medio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crity of knowledge in them; and the words which they uſe are taken now in a quite different ſenſe. How can you know whether the Paſſages brought to you be faithfully alledged? How can you know whether the Books whence they are taken be not ſuppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titious? Of which the Multitude is incredible. But after all, If the Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict of the Fathers be received, the <hi>Roman</hi> Church muſt be caſt, and it will appear that their Religion is but New. Since the <hi>Roman</hi> Church and the Pope boaſt that they can alter the Commandements of God, and make new Articles of Faith, even in that they have a new Religion.</p>
               <p>Now you may ask, Who then ſhall be the Interpreter? Who can give us the true Senſe of Scripture? I anſwer, that ſince the Queſtion here is of an Interpreter that cannot err, and who ſhall always infallibly find out the true Senſe? there is no ſuch in being. God hath not in any place of his Word beſtowed that Gift of
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:100925:17"/>Infallible Interpretation upon the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, no more than upon the <hi>Greek</hi> or the <hi>Syrian.</hi> There is no need of ſuch an Interpreter; for things neceſſary to Salvation are ſo clearly ſet down in Scripture, that they need no Interpretation. Muſt we have an Interpreter to know that God hath created the World, that we muſt love God with all our heart, that the Son of God is dead for us? Now, I ſay, that all the Points neceſſary to Salvation are to be found in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, in terms as clear as theſe.</p>
               <p>The Interpretations uſed by the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors of our Churches, are taken from the Scripture it ſelf, ſo they are not the Interpreters; it is God that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounds himſelf. For Example; When they expound theſe words, <hi>This is my Body;</hi> they take the Interpretation from Jeſus Chriſt himſelf, who ſaith, that it is a <hi>Commemoration of him,</hi> and from three Evangeliſts, who ſay with one accord, that Jeſus Chriſt hath <hi>given Bread</hi> to his Diſciples; and from the words of Chriſt, that he drunk the <hi>Fruit of the Vine,</hi> we expound his other words, <hi>this is my Bloud.</hi> We
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:100925:17"/>expound alſo theſe words of Chriſt, <hi>This is my Body,</hi> from St. <hi>Pauls</hi> words, who (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.) ſaith four times, that we eat Bread in the Lords Supper, and that we break Bread. Certainly, that Apoſtle giveth a clear Expoſition of Chriſt's words, <hi>This is my Body, and this is my Blood,</hi> ſaying, (1 Cor. 10.16.) <hi>The Cup of Bleſſing which we bleſs, is it not the Communion of the Blood of Chriſt? The Bread which we break, is it not the Communion of the Body of Chriſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We alledge alſo thoſe Texts that ſay, that Jeſus Chriſt is no more in this World; that the Heaven doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain him; that Chriſt is like unto us in all things, ſin onely excepted; and that by conſequent he hath not a Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy diſperſed in a Million of ſeveral places at once, and incloſed whole in every Crum of the Hoſt, and in every Drop of the Chalice.</p>
               <p>Likewiſe, when Jeſus ſaith, <hi>Do this in remembrance of me;</hi> We expound not theſe words as the Councel of <hi>Trent</hi> doth, which puts this Senſe up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, I do conſtitute you to be Prieſts, to ſacrifice my Body really
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:100925:18"/>under the <hi>ſpecies</hi> of Bread and Wine but we bring the Interpretation which St. <hi>Paul</hi> addeth (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.26.) <hi>For as often as you eat this Bread and drink this Cup, ye do ſhew the Lords Death.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Conſider alſo, that there is great Difference between a Judgment of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, and a Judgment of Diſcretion. With this laſt we judge of Meats by the Taſte, without giving Laws to any. And it is ſo, that not only Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtours but alſo every one of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, may and doth judge of the true Doctrine. And it is ſo that St. <hi>Paul</hi> will have the Corinthians to judge of his Doctrine (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.15.) <hi>I ſpeak as to wiſe men, judge ye what I ſay.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Of that matter and of the Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of Scripture, I have written a Book purpoſely, which I have dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to your Grace, and which was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to you by Monſieur <hi>de Cabrilles</hi> from me. I asked your Grace at <hi>Liege,</hi> whether you had received it. Your An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer was, that you knew not what was in it: for you have laboured to ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en your ſelf with Reaſons againſt us, but would not take Notice how we anſwer them; and have converſed
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:100925:18"/>much with our Adverſaries, but hid your ſelf from your Servants, who might have cleared your Mind about their Objections, and armed you with Anſwers.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Condemnation of Hereticks.</head>
               <p>Your Grace ſaith farther, that you have deſired to ſee whether the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Hereticks were condemned by Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of our Religion, and whether one man be found in all Antiquity that had the ſame Religion as we, in all Points, Theſe Condemnations of He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks were made by men ſound in the Faith, that were of the ſame Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion as we in all points, who have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned many Errours now received in the <hi>Roman</hi> Church.</p>
               <p>The Councel of <hi>Laodicea</hi> approved by many Univerſal Councels which were held ſince, rejecteth the Books of <hi>Judith, Tobit, Maccabees,</hi> and other Apochryphal Books.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Eliberin</hi> Councel held about the year of the Lord 305 hath made this Canon, <hi>It is decreed, that there ſhall be no Picture in the Church, that the things that
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:100925:19"/>are adored (or ſerved) be not painted up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Walls.</hi> The Councels that have commanded the Adoration of Images are later by 4 or 5 hundred years.</p>
               <p>In the firſt <hi>Nicen</hi> Councel, the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage of the Paſtors of the Church was approved, upon the Remonſtrance of <hi>Paphnutius.</hi> Such is the fourth Canon of the Councel of <hi>Gangra, If any makes a Difference of a married Prieſt, as if he ought not to participate of the Oblation when he doth adminiſter, let him be Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thema.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is the XXXV Canon of the Councel of <hi>Laodicea, Chriſtians muſt not forſake the Church of God, and go to ſerve Angels, and gather Congregations. If any them be found applying himſelf to that ſecret Idolatry, let him be Anathema, becauſe he hath forſaken the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, the Son of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>About the year of the Lord 399, a Councel was held at <hi>Carthage,</hi> of which this is the 23 Canon, <hi>When Service is made at the Altar, the Prayer muſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways be addreſs't to the Father.</hi> The preſent <hi>Roman</hi> Church contradicts that Canon, for in their Service they have Prayers addreſt unto Saints.</p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:100925:19"/>
               <p>This is the 25 Canon of the ſame Councel, <hi>In the Divine Service, let no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing be offered, but the Body and Blood of the Lord, that is, Bread and Wine mingled with Water.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The 16 Canon of the IV Councel of <hi>Carthage,</hi> abſolutely <hi>forbids ſwearing by the Creatures.</hi> To this the Catechiſm of the Councel of <hi>Trent</hi> is contrary, which approveth ſwearing by Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks.</p>
               <p>The 10 Canon of that Councel of <hi>Carthage</hi> ſaith. <hi>Mulier baptizare non pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumat,</hi> Let not a Woman preſume to baptize. The Practiſe of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church is contrary to that.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Milenitan</hi> Councel where St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> was preſent, and of which he hath made the Canons, forbids Appeals from <hi>Africk</hi> to <hi>Rome,</hi> in theſe Words, <hi>It is declared, That if the Prieſts or other Clerks in ſuch Cauſes, as they ſhall have, ſhall complain of the Judgment of their Biſhops, the Biſhops ſhall hear them: But he that will appeal beyond the Seas, let him not be admitted to the Communion by any living in</hi> Africk.</p>
               <p>In the VI Councel of <hi>Carthage,</hi> there is a long Epſtle of the Councel, to
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:100925:20"/>
                  <hi>Celeſtin</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> who, by a new Uſurpation, would draw to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf the Appeals of the Biſhops of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frick;</hi> whereby the Fathers of the Councel beſeech him to receive no more Appeals from their Countrey, forbidding him to ſend any more of his Legats, or to uſe any more forged Canons to raiſe his Dignity, and bring Worldly Pride into the Church of Chriſt. Therefore <hi>Baronius,</hi> and <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmin,</hi> and <hi>Cotton,</hi> Jeſuits, condemn that Councel.</p>
               <p>In the Councel of <hi>Chalcedon,</hi> held in the Year of the Lord 451, the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gats of the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> pretending to the Primacy, and bringing forth a forged Canon of <hi>Nicea,</hi> laboured to hinder the Biſhop of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> from being equal with the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> againſt which, the Councel made this Canon. <hi>The Fathers, with good reaſon, have given Prerogatives to the See of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient</hi> Rome, <hi>becauſe ſhe was the Imperial City. And the hundred and fifty Biſhops of the firſt Councel of</hi> Conſtantinople, <hi>moved with the like conſideration, have attributed to the moſt holy See of New</hi> Rome, <hi>which is</hi> Conſtantinople, <hi>equal
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:100925:20"/>Priviledges; judging with good reaſon, that the City honoured with the Empire and the Senate, and which hath the ſame Prerogatives as the Antient</hi> Rome <hi>Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial, ought to be magnified as much as</hi> [Rome] <hi>it ſelf in Eccleſiaſtical things.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Popes of our time and their Advocates condemn that Council, not only becauſe it equalleth the Biſhop of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> with that of <hi>Rome,</hi> but chiefly becauſe it groundeth the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eminence of the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> upon the Dignity of the City, becauſe <hi>Rome</hi> is the Capital City of the Empire, and not upon the Succeſſion in the Apoſtle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of St. <hi>Peter.</hi> For the Fathers of that Council do not acknowledge him in that Quality.</p>
               <p>The Council of <hi>Aurange</hi> condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Merits in the 12th Canon, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>God loveth us, according as we ſhall be by his Grace, and not ſuch as we ſhall be through our Merits.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the Year of Our Lord 549, <hi>Repa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Cathage</hi> called a Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod, in which <hi>Vigilius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> was anathematized as an Heretick <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tychian:</hi> And <hi>Honorius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> was condemned by the VI and
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:100925:21"/>the VII Univerſal Councils, as an He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retick <hi>Monothelite.</hi> In the VI Council of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> aſſembled again in the Palace of <hi>Trulle,</hi> in the 17 and the 77 Canon, the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly, and by name condemned, and is commanded to hinder no more the cohabitation of Prieſts with their Wives, and to Faſt no more on the Lords Day, upon pain of Depoſition, or Excommunication. Whence it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth by the way, that the <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Eaſtern</hi> Church, in which that Council was celebrated, in which that Council was celebrated, was not ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, ſince ſhe preſcribed Laws to her.</p>
               <p>In the Year 754, a Council com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed of 338 Biſhops, was held at <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople,</hi> in which it was decreed, that Images ſhould be removed out of Churches, and the worſhip of them was forbidden. There alſo the Bread of the Euchariſt is called the <hi>Image,</hi> and the <hi>Figure</hi> of the Body of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>But in the Year 787 the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs <hi>Irene</hi> aſſembled another Council againſt that Council at <hi>Nicea,</hi> in which Images were ſet up again, and
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:100925:21"/>the Worſhip of them was commanded upon Pain of <hi>Anathema.</hi> But in the year 794, the Emperour <hi>Charles</hi> the Great, cauſed that Council of <hi>Nicea</hi> to be condemned by another Council aſſembled at <hi>Frankford,</hi> although he knew, that Pope <hi>Adrian</hi> was of a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Opinion, and had defended that Council of <hi>Nicea</hi> by an expreſs Book.</p>
               <p>This is, My Lord, the Condemnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Errours about our Controverſies, which I find in the ancient Councils. Neither could I find any ancient Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil, which (in matters of Faith) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demns the Doctrine that we profeſs. For the Chronicle of <hi>Gaultier,</hi> (which was ſhewed to your Grace,) repreſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth things falſly, and doth not agree with other Authors of his Religion, who juſtifie us againſt moſt of his Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumnies.</p>
               <p>I am ready to undergo any Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, if in the 500 years, which your Grace mentions, one only man be found, that had a Religion any whit like the preſent Religion of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church. In the ancient Church the publick Service was celebrated in the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:100925:22"/>vulgar Tongue underſtood by the People. The Laity received the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion in the two kinds. The read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Scripture was not prohibited to the People. The Church did not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve <hi>Purgatory.</hi> Before the year 370 of the Lord, no Tract is found of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation of Saints. There was no Mention of <hi>Roman</hi> Indulgences, nor of the Treaſure of the Church, in which the Pope hath laid up the Overplus of the penal Works, and Satisfactions of Saints and Monks, which he diſtributes among the People by his Indulgences. In thoſe days they made no Images of God. They worſhipped not the Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of Saints. They adored not the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated Hoſt with Worſhip of <hi>Latria.</hi> They ſpake not of Accidents without a Subject. They believed not, that Mice could gnaw the Body of Chriſt, or that it could be blown away be the Wind, or ſtole or devoured by Beaſts, as we are taught in the Beginning of the Miſſal.</p>
               <p>In thoſe days, the Biſhops of <hi>Aſia, Africa, Aegypt, Graece,</hi> &amp;c. took no Oath of Allegiance to the <hi>Roman</hi> Biſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>op in their Ordination, and took no
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:100925:22"/>Letters of Inveſtiture from him. In thoſe Days they believed not that Jeſus Chriſt had eaten his own Body in the Communion. They believed not, that it was in the Prieſts Power to create his Creator. The Pope did not ſtyle himſelf God and the Divine Majeſty. He boaſted not, that he could not err, and that he was the Sovereign Judge of Controverſies. He drew no Souls out of <hi>Purgatory.</hi> He took not upon him the Power of adding to the Creed. He canonized no Saints. He gave no Pardons of two or three hundred years. He diſpenſed not with Vows and Oaths. He diſpenſed no with Vows and Oaths. He neither gave nor took away King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms. He put no Kingdom in Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict.</p>
               <p>In thoſe days, the Bleſſed Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> was not called the Queen of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and the Lady of the World. The Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> did not beſtow ſeveral Offices upon Saints, charging one to look over ſuch a Country, another to ſuch a Diſeaſe, another to ſuch a Trade. They ſpake not in thoſe days of <hi>Franciſcan</hi> Fryars, nor of <hi>Dominicans,</hi> nor of <hi>Capucins,</hi> nor of <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> nor of <hi>Beads, Roſaries, Agnus Dei,</hi> and the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:100925:23"/>like Commodities. In a Word, the <hi>Roman</hi> Religion is a Religion ſpick and ſpan new, and an horrible defa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of the ancient Religion taught by Chriſt and his Apoſtles.</p>
               <p>If Your Grace hath ſuch a great De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to be inſtructed about Antiquity, you may deſire one of thoſe that take upon them to inſtruct you, to give you but one Example upon any of the forementioned Points. I am ſure that they will never undertake it, it being utterly impoſſible.</p>
               <p>I could ſhew to Your Grace, that all theſe Inventions were deviſed to ſerve the Gain and Ambition of the Pope and his Clergy. But I will paſs to that which Your Grace addeth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Pope's Primacy.</head>
               <p>From thence you paſs to the Pope's Primacy, and ſpeak thus; I ſought to be informed, whether all the Weſtern Churches had not always acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> to be the Primate and the Head of the viſible Church, eſtabliſhed by our Lord for the Conduct of the ſame; and ſeeing
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:100925:23"/>the Proteſtants were ſo far from reje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting the firſt five Centuries, that they often both in their Sermons and Books, quote and produce the Fathers that writ in thoſe Ages. I thought the ſhorteſt way for my Information would be to ſee what were the Sentiments of thoſe Fathers in the controverted Points.</p>
               <p>Truly my Lord, that ſhort way which you ſay you have taken, is of an infinite Length, and indeed there is no end of it. It would have been a far ſhorter way to have asked of the ableſt men of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it may be found in Gods Word, that God hath eſtabliſhed the Pope Succeſſor of St. <hi>Peter</hi> in his Apoſtle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and in his Primacy over the Univerſal Church. They would have freely confeſt unto you, that the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scripture ſaith nothing of it, and that it is a Tradition about which we have no Commandment of God.</p>
               <p>I obſerve alſo, that you ſpeak only of the Weſtern Churches, whence I ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that he who ſuggeſted theſe things to your Grace, knows that the <hi>Eaſtern</hi> and the <hi>African</hi> Church never
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:100925:24"/>acknowledged the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> in that Quality and Character. Now thoſe Churches were then greater than the Weſtern, as alſo they are ancient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. Now by the Councils approved both by the Weſtern and the Eaſtern Churches, which I have already al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged to your Grace, the Pride of the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> who began then to lift up himſelf is cenſured.</p>
               <p>And though you had proved that the Weſtern have always acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Pope as Head of the Church, it availeth nothing, unleſs it be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved alſo, that his Primacy then conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in doing thoſe things which he doth now. Did he then boaſt that he could not err? Did he vaunt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf as Sovereign Judge of the Senſe and Interpretation of Scripture? Did he give Indulgences? Did he draw Souls out of <hi>Purgatory?</hi> Did he give and take away Kingdom? Did he call himſelf God? Did he boaſt that he hath Power to add unto the Creed? For in vain do we diſpute about Titles, when the things are dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent.</p>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:100925:24"/>
               <p>I would alſo beſeech you Grace to ſee whether you be not abuſed; for indeed many Paſſages in the Fathers are found, which ſay that the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> is Succeſſor to St. <hi>Peter:</hi> But they ſpeak of the Succeſſion in the Charge of Biſhop of the City of <hi>Rome,</hi> not in the Apoſtleſhip, or in the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy over the Univerſal Church. And it is very remarkable, that all the Examples of the Popes Authority brought out of Antiquity, are within the Limits of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire. And that it cannot be found for above a thouſand years after our Saviours time, that the Biſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> did in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termeddle with the Affairs of Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es without the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire, as of the <hi>Perſian, Armenian,</hi> and <hi>Indian</hi> Churches. In all that time he never gave them any Laws, he never recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved any Appeal from them.</p>
               <p>And that you may ſee what was the Face of the ancient Church in that Point, I will lay down before your Grace ſome Examples according to the Order of the Ages.</p>
               <p>For the firſt Age we find that St. <hi>Peter</hi> writ his laſt Epiſtle being near
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:100925:25"/>his Death, as he ſaith himſelf in the firſt Chapter; and then, or never it was time for him to ſay, now my Death is at Hand, but I leave you for my Succeſſor the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> to whom I will have the Univerſal Church be ſubject; but of that he ſaith no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, nor takes any of thoſe Titles up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him which the Pope now attributes unto himſelf. St. <hi>Peter</hi> being dead, if there had been any Queſtion about chooſing a Head for the Univerſal Church in his Room, no Doubt but that ſome Apoſtle as St. <hi>James</hi> or St. <hi>John</hi> muſt have ſucceeded him; for St. <hi>John</hi> outlived St. <hi>Peter</hi> about thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty years, but no ſuch thing was done. In the ſame. Age lived <hi>Dionyſius Areo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagite,</hi> to whom are aſcribed by them of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, the Books of Eccleſiaſtical Hierarchy. Reaſon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired that he ſhould ſpeak of the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign Hierarch, who now is called the Pope. Yet he ſpeaks never a word of him, he deſcribeth all the Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical Offices and Degrees, making no Mention of the Head of the Church, for he did not acknowledge any.</p>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:100925:25"/>
               <p>We find by the Eccleſiaſtical Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, that in that Age and long after, the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> was elected by the Suffrages of the Clegy of that Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oceſan Church, with the Conſent of their People; An evident Proof that they believed not in thoſe days, that the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> was Head of the Univerſal Church. For had he been ſo, the Univerſal Church muſt have contributed to his Election; the People of <hi>Rome</hi> having no right to give a Head to the Church of all the World.</p>
               <p>That Age did ſwarm with Hereſies, which the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> did not condemn, nor had any Cogniſance of them. None that we read of were condemned by any Council for not obeying the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſing to be judged by him. Our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries themſelves do not alledge any thing from the <hi>Roman</hi> Church of that Age, but only ſome falſe decre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Epiſtles of the Popes, which <hi>Baro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> and <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> and <hi>Binnius</hi> and many others, acknowledge to be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged.</p>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:100925:26"/>
               <p>In the ſecond Century our Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries find nothing for the Popes Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy. Only towards the end of that Age, upon the Queſtion about the Day of the Celebration of <hi>Eaſter, Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> ſeparated himſelf from the Communion of diverſe of the Oriental Churches, becauſe they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſely obſerved the 14th day of the Moon of <hi>March</hi> for the day of <hi>Eaſter.</hi> For which Action, <hi>Victor</hi> was ſharply taken up by other Biſhops, and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly by <hi>Irenaeus,</hi> as <hi>Euſebius</hi> witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth in the V Book, and 25 Chapter of his Hiſtory.</p>
               <p>The third Age affords us many Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples to the contrary. In the year of our Lord 217 <hi>Agrippinus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Carthage</hi> aſſembled a Council in <hi>Africa,</hi> in which it was reſolved and defined, that the Baptiſm of Hereticks was no Baptiſm. This was againſt the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and whether of the two was in the Right it is not material; It is enough that thereby it appeareth, that the Church of <hi>Africa</hi> was not then ſubject to that of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:100925:26"/>
               <p>In the year of our Lord 256 <hi>Cypri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> Succeſſor of <hi>Agrippinus</hi> began to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend his Predeceſſors Doctrine. There being then a Diſcord between <hi>Corneli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> and one <hi>Novatianus,</hi> whereby the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> was in Trouble, <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſent two Legats to <hi>Rome,</hi> to compoſe the Difference, thereby taking as much Authority over the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> as the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> uſe to exerciſe in the like Caſes. In all his Epiſtles to <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nelius,</hi> he giveth him no other Title but that of <hi>Brother,</hi> and acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth him not for his Superiour.</p>
               <p>The Contention about rebaptizing of Hereticks grew hot between him, and <hi>Stephen</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> even to down-right ill Words. In the Epiſtle to <hi>Pompeius,</hi> which is the 74, <hi>Cyprian</hi> calls <hi>Stephen</hi> the Champion of Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks. proud, ignorant, imprudent, an Enemy to Chriſtians, preferring Falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood before Truth, and Anti-Chriſt before Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Moreover, he aſſembled a Council of 87 <hi>African</hi> Biſhops, who condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Stephen</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> and his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and that in Terms worſe than
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:100925:27"/>
                  <hi>Cyprian</hi> had given him. About the ſame time St. <hi>Firmilianus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Caeſarea</hi> in <hi>Cappadocia,</hi> a man of great Authority alſo, bitterly reviled <hi>Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phen.</hi> From theſe things it ſufficiently appears, that theſe Biſhops were far from thinking themſelves ſubject to the Biſhop of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In that Age our Adverſaries find nothing for the Pope's Primacy; no Appeals to him from Churches, either far or near; no Laws given to the Univerſal Church; onely ſome forged Decretal Epiſtles of the Biſhops of <hi>Rome,</hi> of thoſe times are produced, whoſe falſhood is acknowledged by the moſt Learned of the <hi>Roman</hi> Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. In thoſe Epiſtles the Pope is made to ſpeak as a Maſter, having power over all the Emperours and Biſhops of the World; Whereas the Biſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> then confined the exerciſe of their Power to their own Dioceſs; not preſuming to give Laws to any other Churches, much leſs to their Temporal Governours.</p>
               <p>Of thoſe three firſt Ages, Pope <hi>Pius</hi> the Second in his Epiſtle to <hi>Martin Mayer,</hi> which is the 188. ſpeaks thus,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:100925:27"/>
                  <hi>Every one then lived for himſelf, and little Reverence was deferred to the</hi> Roman <hi>Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the year of our Lord 312. the Emperour <hi>Conſtantine</hi> being convert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Chriſtian Religion, appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Judges in the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> Caſe, <hi>Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiades</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> being one of them. But the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> having com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained of his Judgment, the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour commanded that their Cauſe ſhould be judged again by the Synod of <hi>Arles,</hi> who had power to confirm or diſannul the Judgment of <hi>Melchia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des,</hi> and his Fellow-Judges.</p>
               <p>Under that Emperour, the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Church being delivered from Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions, a new Order and Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution was made over all the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire, to which <hi>Sylveſter</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> was not called. His Legend ſaith untruly, that he baptized <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine,</hi> and healed him of a Lepro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie; but upon that groundleſs Fable was built <hi>the Donation of Conſtantine,</hi> by which the Emperour is pretended to have given unto the Pope one half of his Empire.</p>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:100925:28"/>
               <p>The ſame Emperour, in the year 325. aſſembled a General Council out of the whole Empire, in which <hi>Sylveſter</hi> did not preſide, but <hi>Hozius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Corduba</hi> in <hi>Spain,</hi> of whom our Adverſaries falſly ſay, that he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſided in that Council as the Pope's Legate: A thing repugnant to the Teſtimony of <hi>Euſebius, Theodoret,</hi> and <hi>Sozomen,</hi> and to the Acts of the <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cene</hi> Council, in which <hi>Hozius</hi> ſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the firſt without ſtyling himſelf the Pope's Legat; and after him <hi>Vitus</hi> and <hi>Vincentius</hi> Deputies of the Biſhop of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To the Emperour <hi>Conſtantine</hi> ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded his Son <hi>Conſtantius,</hi> who fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring the <hi>Arrians,</hi> baniſhed <hi>Liberius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> and gave him five hundred Crowns to maintain him in his Exile. But <hi>Liberius,</hi> to be reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to his Biſhoprick, joyned with the <hi>Arrians,</hi> and ſubſcribed their Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, in their Aſſembly at <hi>Sirmium.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the year 381. the Emperour <hi>Theodoſius</hi> called a General Council at <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> to which <hi>Damaſus</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> came not, nor ſent any Legate to it; that Council being aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:100925:28"/>without his conſent. In that Council Hereſies were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, and the Order of the Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>archs was altered, without asking the Advice of <hi>Damaſus.</hi> Yet that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil is one of the firſt four Oecume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical Councils.</p>
               <p>About the ſame time, <hi>Ambroſe</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Milan</hi> refuſed to adminiſter the Communion to the Emperour <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> for a Murther committed by his Guards at <hi>Theſſalonica. Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe</hi> did this without taking the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of <hi>Damaſus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> his Neighbour. Such an action in our dayes would be High Treaſon againſt the Pope. For it is one of the Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental Laws of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, that Kings cannot be bound by Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, or excommunicated but by the Pope's Order.</p>
               <p>That I may not gather here a great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er number of Examples, I have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged before many Councils that have condemned Popes of Hereſie, and have forbidden them to ſend Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gates, and receive Appeals from Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Churches.</p>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:100925:29"/>
               <p>The firſt Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> (that I read of) who took upon him to govern the Church as Succeſſor of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> was <hi>Leo</hi> the Firſt, about the year of our Lord 450. For before him the Preeminence which was claimed by the <hi>Roman</hi> Biſhops, was grounded on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon ſome miſtaken or falſified Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons of Councils; and thoſe in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of the dignity of the City, which was the chief City of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire: For out of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire the Biſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> claimed no Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riority.</p>
               <p>Some Paſſages are found, true or falſe, in which the Biſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> are ſtyled the firſt Biſhops of the whole World, and Preſidents over the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Church: But the Reaſon of it was, that the Ancients called the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Emperours, Governours and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the World, and it is frequent in their Writings to call the Empire <hi>Orbis Romanus,</hi> the <hi>Roman</hi> World. The Truth of this is evident, becauſe the ſame Titles are many times given to the other Patriarchs, or chief Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire, <hi>viz.</hi> To the Biſhop of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> to him
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:100925:29"/>of <hi>Antioch,</hi> and to him of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> who are alſo called the Heads and So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereigns of all; and are ſaid to have the Care of all the Churches. Thus <hi>Gregory Nazianzen</hi> in his Oration up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Athanaſius</hi> ſaith, <hi>That the Charge of the People of</hi> Alexandria <hi>was committed unto him, which is as much as if one ſaid the Government of all the World.</hi> And in the ſame place he ſaith, that <hi>Atha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſius gave Laws unto all the World.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Baſil</hi> ſaith, that <hi>Meletius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Antioch,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Baſil. Ep: <hi>50.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>did preſide over the whole Body of the Church. Theodoret</hi> in his Book of Hereſies, in the Chapter where he ſpeaks of <hi>Neſtorius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople,</hi> calls him alſo the Biſhop <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>of the whole habitable World.</hi> Wherefore alſo the Patriarch of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople</hi> is called the Oecumenical or Univerſal Biſhop in the Councils of that Age.</p>
               <p>For this Rule was conſtituted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Patriarchs of the <hi>Roman</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, that each of them was to take Care of all the Churches of the whole <hi>Roman</hi> Empire: but that Power was never extended beyond the Limits of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire. Yea, ſome Paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:100925:30"/>are found in which that general Dignity is attributed unto all Biſhops that were eminent in Holineſs; as <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſil</hi> ſaith to <hi>Ambroſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Idem ep. <hi>55.</hi>
                  </note> that <hi>God had raiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him to the Dignity of the Apoſtles.</hi> And <hi>Sidonius</hi> calls <hi>Lupus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Troyes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Sidon. lib. <hi>6.</hi> ep. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> the <hi>Biſhop of Biſhops, and the firſt Prelate of all the World.</hi> In thoſe times all Biſhops were called Popes.</p>
               <p>For the Popes Primacy Your Grace alledgeth St. <hi>Hierom,</hi> who writing to <hi>Damaſus,</hi> and acknowledging no other Preeminence than that of Jeſus Chriſt, ſaid, <hi>I am in Communion with thy Beatitude,</hi> that is, <hi>with St.</hi> Peter's <hi>Chair.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſee nothing there that favoureth the Popes Primacy over the Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal Church. For (as I mentioned be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) the Biſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> were held St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Succeſſors in his Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment over the <hi>Roman</hi> Church; which Government they held to have been founded by St. <hi>Peter,</hi> and I would not diſpute about that. But they were not held Succeſſors of St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Apoſtleſhip, nor of his Primacy. Say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to a man, I am of thy Communion, is not acknowledging him Head of
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:100925:30"/>the Univerſal Church. So much many be ſaid to any Biſhop that is ſound in the Faith; yea, to any true Believer we may ſay, that we muſt be of his Communion, and that he that gather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not with him, is a Scatterer. There were then held to be three Chairs of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> one at <hi>Rome,</hi> another in <hi>Alexandria,</hi> another in <hi>Antioch.</hi> The Biſhops of theſe Cities ſtyled them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Succeſſors of St. <hi>Peter</hi> in the Government of thoſe Churches, not in the Apoſtleſhip. And there were always Piques and Quarrels between thoſe three Sees. <hi>Gregory</hi> the Firſt, Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> in the 37 Epiſtle of his VI Book, ſaith that thoſe three Chairs are but one See, upon which three Biſhops are ſitting, and he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgeth them his Equals, and that it belongs not to him to command them.</p>
               <p>But they that ſhewed to Your Grace that Authority of St. <hi>Hierom,</hi> had more Wit than to ſhew you other Paſſages of his, in which he debaſeth very much the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> and giveth no good Character of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Church of his Age. In his Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:100925:31"/>to <hi>Euagrius</hi> he ſaith; <hi>In what part ſoever a man is a Biſhop, whether it be at</hi> Rome, <hi>or at</hi> Agobio, <hi>whether at</hi> Conſtantinople <hi>or</hi> Regio, <hi>they have the ſame Dignity and Authority; Power and Wealth, or Meanneſs and Poverty, do not make one greater or lower than ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. By their Place they are all Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors of the Apoſtles.</hi> And becauſe ſome alledged the Example of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church for preferring the Deacon before the Prieſt, he anſwereth, <hi>Why doeſt thou alledge to me the Cuſtom of one City?</hi> ſhewing that that was not to be a Rule to the Univerſal Church.</p>
               <p>His Cuſtom is to call <hi>Rome Babylon,</hi> and the <hi>Harlot,</hi> and to exhort devout Perſons to come out of her. And in his Preface upon the Book of <hi>Didymus</hi> of the Holy Ghoſt, he ſpeaks thus, <hi>When I was in</hi> Babylon, <hi>and was an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitant of the</hi> Harlot <hi>clad in Purple, and lived after the Laws of the</hi> Roman <hi>Citizens, I would prate ſomewhat about the Holy Ghoſt, and dedicate my Work to the Biſhop of the City. But behold that Pot which is ſeen in</hi> Jeremiah <hi>after the Staff on the North-ſide, begins to boyl, and the Senate of the Phariſees be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:100925:31"/>to cry out,</hi> meaning by the Senate of the Phariſees, the Eccleſiaſtical <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Senate.</p>
               <p>And in the Epiſtle to <hi>Marcella</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the name of <hi>Paula</hi> and <hi>Euſtochium,</hi> exhorting <hi>Marcella</hi> to come out of <hi>Rome,</hi> and to retire to <hi>Bethlehem, I eſteem</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that this place of</hi> Beth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lehem <hi>is holier than the</hi> Tarpeian <hi>Rock,</hi> (meaning the <hi>Roman</hi> Capitol) <hi>which having ſo often been ſtruck with Lightning from Heaven, ſheweth that it is diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing unto God. Read St.</hi> Johns <hi>Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, and ſee what is foretold of the</hi> Hatlot <hi>clad with Purple, and of the Blaſphemy written on her forehead, and of the ſeven Mountains, and of the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Waters; fly from her my People, and be not Partaker of her Sins, leaſt you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive of her Plagues: It is fallen, it is fallen,</hi> &amp;c. But being gone from <hi>Rome</hi> into <hi>Syria,</hi> and living there in perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Quarrels with the Clergy of that Country, he was conſtrained to have Recourſe unto his old Maſter <hi>Dama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi> (for he had been his Secretary) and to write to him thoſe kind Letters which you alledge.</p>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:100925:32"/>
               <p>After <hi>Hierom</hi> you bring St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> in theſe words, <hi>Shall we doubt whether we muſt reſt in the Churches Lap, which by Succeſſion hath always had Sovereign Authority in the Apoſtolick Chair?</hi> That Paſſage is found in the Book <hi>de utili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate credendi,</hi> in the 17 Chapter, but otherwiſe ſet down than Your Grace alledgeth. Diſputing againſt the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicheans,</hi> with whom Scripture had no Authority, he uſeth humane and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable Proofs to exhort men to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace the Chriſtian Religion. He ſaith then, <hi>We ſeeing ſuch a great Aſſiſtance of God, and ſo great Proficiency &amp; Improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment advance, ſhall we doubt to enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lap of that Church,</hi> [not the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> but <hi>Catholick</hi> Church] <hi>which (even to the Confeſſion of Mankind) from the Apoſtolick See, by the Succeſſions of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, while the Hereticks in vain barked about her,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>hath arrived at the height of Authority</hi> [that is, to be the eſtabliſht Religion.]</p>
               <p>In this Paſſage St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> neither mentioneth nor appears to have thought of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church. And although the Chair of <hi>Rome</hi> had been named in it, yet this would avail no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:100925:32"/>for the Primacy of the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> over the Univerſal Church. For the Primacy of the Apoſtolick Chairs is attributed by the Ancients no leſs to the Church of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> of <hi>Antioch,</hi> of <hi>Jeruſalem, &amp;c.</hi> than to the Church of <hi>Rome. Sozomen</hi> ſpeaks thus of the Council of <hi>Nice,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Soz. hiſt. lib. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>16.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>There met among the Biſhops that held Apoſtolick Sees,</hi> Macarius <hi>Biſhop of</hi> Jeruſalem, Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtathius <hi>Biſhop of</hi> Antioch <hi>upon the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver</hi> Orontes, <hi>and</hi> Alexander <hi>near the</hi> Mareotid Marſhes. And again,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>idem</hi> 4.24.</note> of the <hi>Epheſine</hi> Council, <hi>Cyrillus Prelate of the Apoſtolick See,</hi> meaning <hi>Jeruſalem. Ruffinus</hi> in the ſecond Book, chap. 21. In <hi>Alexandria Timothy,</hi> in <hi>Jeruſalem John, reſtored the Apoſtolick Sees. The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>odoret</hi> in the fifth Book of his Hiſtory chap. 9. calls <hi>Antioch the moſt ancient Church and wholly Apoſtolick.</hi> St. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin</hi> in his 162 Epiſtle, ſpeaks of the Apoſtolick Sees in the plural, ſaying, that <hi>Cecilian might have reſerved his Cauſe to the Judgment of the Apoſtolick Sees.</hi> We have alledged <hi>Baſil</hi> before, ſaying that St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lan</hi> had the Apoſtolick Preheminence, and <hi>Hierom</hi> ſaying, that all Biſhops are
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:100925:33"/>Succeſſors of the Apoſtles. <hi>Sidonius</hi> in the firſt Epiſtle of the 6. Book, ſaith that <hi>Lupus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Troyes</hi> had alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſet nine times five years in the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolick See.</p>
               <p>They do then abuſe your Grace, that make you believe that <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſpeaks only of the Apoſtolick See of the <hi>Roman</hi> Biſhop, ſeeing that the Primacy of the Apoſtolick See, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longed to ſo many other Biſhops. And though in that place St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> had ſpoken of the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, he had not thereby excluded the other Biſhops from the ſame Dignity. He that ſaith the King of <hi>France</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyeth the Royal Preeminence, doth not thereby deny to the Kings of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and <hi>Spain</hi> their Authority in their own Countries.</p>
               <p>Here it is obſervable, that St. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin</hi> was never ſubject to the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> that he never took an Oath of Fidelity to him, that when he was ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted Biſhop, he took no Letters of Inveſtiture from him, and paid him no Annates for his Entry. He was one of thoſe that made the Canons of the <hi>Milevitan</hi> Council, which for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bad
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:100925:33"/>the Appeals from <hi>Africa</hi> to <hi>Rome;</hi> and one of thoſe that made that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrance to <hi>Celeſtin</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> that he ſhould for the time to come abſtain from ſending Legats into <hi>Afri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca,</hi> and medling with their Buſineſſes, and uſing Suppoſititious Canons to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance his Authority. The Biſhops of <hi>Africa</hi> were of the ſame Faith with the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> and ſpake to him in reſpectful Terms, becauſe of the Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of the Imperial City, and becauſe they believed that St. <hi>Peter</hi> died at <hi>Rome,</hi> and had founded that Chair among many others. But if the Biſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> had taken upon them the Title of God, and boaſted that they could not err; if they had taken up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them to canonize Saints, to give Indulgences, to draw Souls out of Purgatory, to alter the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God, and to add unto the Creed; thoſe <hi>African</hi> Biſhops would have beſtowed their Cenſures upon him as freely as they did upon any other who fell into Hereſie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:100925:34"/>
               <head>Of the Sacrifice of the Maſs.</head>
               <p>For the Sacrifice of the Maſs, Your Grace alledgeth two Paſſages out of St. <hi>Auſtin.</hi> The one ſaith, <hi>That the Catholick Faith ſuffers not that the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of the Body and Blood of the Lord be offered for thoſe that are not bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized.</hi> In the other, ſpeaking of his dead Mother, he ſaith, that the <hi>Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of our Ranſom was offered for her, when her Body was upon the Brink of the Grave.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There is nothing more eaſie than to deceive one that will be deceived, and hath no Knowledge in the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> declareth his Mind upon this point very often, and tells us that the Euchariſt is called the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of the Body and Blood of Jeſus Chriſt, becauſe it is the Sign and Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure of his Body and Blood; and that the Signs are ordinarily called by the Names of the things which they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent. Thus in his Epiſt. 23 to <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niface, Hath not Chriſt been once ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in himſelf? And yet he is ſacrificed unto the People in a ſacred Sign; and
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:100925:34"/>he doth not lye, who being asked, anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, that he is ſacrificed. For if the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments had not ſome Likeneſs to the things of which they are Sacraments, they could not be Sacraments. Now by Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of that Likeneſs they take often the name of the very things.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Add to this the Canon,<note place="margin">De conſecr. diſt. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>48.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>i. e.</hi> the <hi>Roman</hi> Code of Canon Law. <hi>The Immolation of the Fleſh, which is done by the hands of the Prieſt is called the Paſſion, the Death, and the crucifying of Jeſus Chriſt, not in Truth, but by a ſignificant Myſtery.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is then the Senſe of theſe pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of St. <hi>Auſtin;</hi> that the Euchariſt is the Sacrifice of the ſame Price, becauſe it is the Sign and the Sacrament of it, and becauſe the Signs take commonly the name of the thing ſignified; as the ſame Father ſaith,<note place="margin">St. <hi>Aug.</hi> quaeſt. <hi>55.</hi> in Levit. Idem con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Adi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant. c. <hi>12.</hi> Theod. dialog. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>The ſignifying thing uſeth to take the name of the thing ſignified. And the Lord hath made no Difficulty to ſay, This is my Body, when he gave the Sign of his Body.</hi> And <hi>Theodoret</hi> expounding theſe words, <hi>This is my Body,</hi> ſaith, that the <hi>Lord hath given to the Sign the name of his Body.</hi>
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:100925:35"/>And <hi>Tertullian,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Tertul. <hi>contr.</hi> Marc. 4.40.</note> 
                  <hi>This is my Body,</hi> that is, <hi>the Sign of my Body.</hi> Indeed the Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſt is called a <hi>Sacrifice of our Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom,</hi> in the ſame manner, as in the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of the Sacrament, the Bread is called the Body of Chriſt; and in the ſame manner as the Cup is called the New Teſtament, becauſe it is the Sacrament and Memorial of the ſame; for neither the Cup nor that which is in it is a Teſtament. St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> knew that Jeſus Chriſt hath wholly paid our Ranſom on the Croſs, and that there is no other Ranſom but the Death of Jeſus Chriſt to redeem us: now the Euchariſt is not the Death of Jeſus Chriſt. And if to apply the Sacrifice of the Croſs unto us, we muſt ſacrifice Jeſus Chriſt again; by the ſame Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to apply the Death of Jeſus Chriſt unto us, we muſt put him to Death again.</p>
               <p>But what can we ask more, ſince our Adverſaries confeſs that Jeſus Chriſt did not offer himſelf in Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice in the Euchariſt, and put that Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice among the unwritten Traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons? So much <hi>Bellarmine</hi> confeſſeth in the firſt Book of the Maſs, <hi>Chap.</hi> 27.
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:100925:35"/>§ <hi>Quinta. The Oblation</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>which is made after the Conſecration belongeth to the Integrity of the Sacrifice, but not to the Eſſence of it; which is proved, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Lord did not make that Obla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion nor the Sacrifice at the firſt.</hi> And both <hi>Baronius</hi> and the Jeſuit <hi>Salmeron</hi> put the Maſs and the Sacrifice of the ſame among the unwritten Traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
               <p>As for the Paſſage you alledge out of the Catechiſms of <hi>Cyrill</hi> of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> I need ſay no more but that the Book which you quote is ſuppoſititious, whoſe Style is far different from that of the other beforegoing. God hath permitted that an evident Sign of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gery ſhould be in that Book; the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor exhorteth his Hearers, that they be no more Spectators of the Combats of Gladiators of the Amphitheater, and of the Horſe-races in the Hippo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drome: But ſince <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> was Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, there hath been no Spectacles in the Amphitheater or Hippodrome. <hi>Geſner</hi> in his <hi>Bibliotheca</hi> ſaith, that he hath ſeen thoſe <hi>Catechiſms</hi> in the Libra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of <hi>Ausburg,</hi> under the name of <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Conſtantinople.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:100925:36"/>
               <head>Of the Invocation of Saints.</head>
               <p>For the Invocation of Saints, Your Grace alledgeth St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> in the Book of Widows, where he ſaith, <hi>That we muſt pray to the Angels that have the keeping of us, and to the Saints and Martyrs, of whom we may expect Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance.</hi> St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> writ that Book when he was a new Chriſtian, but he changed his Language after that time: for in his Oration for <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten long after, he ſaith <hi>Thou alone, O Lord, muſt be called upon and prayed to. And</hi> Mary <hi>was the Temple of God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>St. Ambr.</hi> l. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>12.</hi> de Sp. Sanct.</note> 
                  <hi>but ſhe was not God; wherefore we muſt worſhip God alone who wrought in that Temple.</hi> And a little before, <hi>We read, that we muſt not worſhip any but God, for it is written, Thou ſhalt worſhip the Lord thy God, and him only ſhalt thou ſerve.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Comment upon the Epiſtle to the <hi>Romans</hi> aſcribed to <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the firſt Chapter ſaith, <hi>Addreſs is made to the King by Colonels and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours, becauſe the King is a man and knoweth not to whom he ought to commit
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:100925:36"/>the Adminiſtration of the State; but to get Gods Favour who is ignorant of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, (for he knoweth what men are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving) there is no need of any ones Suffrage to help us, but of a devout Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit.</hi> And upon <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 1. <hi>Chriſt holds the Primacy in all things; wherefore if any beleive that he muſt have Devotion for ſome Element, or for ſome of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels and Powers, let him know that he is in an Errour.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> in his firſt Sermon of Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitence, ſpeaks thus, <hi>God muſt be pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to without an Interceſſor.</hi> And upon <hi>Heb.</hi> 1. in his third Homily, <hi>Why do you look up to Angels, gaping after them? They are Servants to the Son of God, ſent to ſeveral places in your behalf.</hi> And in the eighteenth Homily upon the Epiſtle to the <hi>Romans,</hi> towards the end, <hi>To whom wilt thou have Recourſe? Whoſe Help wilt thou implore? Wilt thou call upon</hi> Abraham? <hi>But he cannot hear thee. Wilt thou call upon thoſe Virgins? But they will give thee none of their Oyl. Wilt thou call upon thy Father or thy Grand-father? but none of them, though never ſo holy, hath Power to alter that Judgment. Theſe things being conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:100925:37"/>thou muſt venerate him, and pray to him alone, who hath Power to blot out that Obligation, and to put out that Flame.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">S. <hi>Aug.</hi> Enchir. c. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Of God alone we muſt ask the Good which we hope to do, or hope to obtain by our good Works.</hi> And in the Book of the Quantity of the Soul, 34 <hi>chap. God alone muſt be ſerved by the Soul, for he alone is the Maker of it.</hi> And in the laſt Chapter of the Book of the true Religion. <hi>Let the Worſhip of dead men be none of our Religion; for if they have lived godly, they are not ſo diſpoſed to ſeek ſuch Honours: but they would have us worſhip him, by whoſe Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumination they rejoyce that we are Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tners of their Dignity. We muſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore honour them by way of Imitation, and not worſhip them on the account of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</hi> And he ſpeaks thus to God,<note place="margin">Idem l. confeſs. c. <hi>42.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Whom can I find to reconcile me with thee? Muſt I addreſs my ſelf to Angels? By what Prayers? By what Sacraments? Many have tryed theſe ways. and are fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len to the Deſire of curious Viſions, and have deſerved to be deceived.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tertullian</hi> in the thirtieth Chapter of his <hi>Apologetick,</hi> ſpeaks thus, <hi>I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:100925:37"/>ask theſe things of any but him of whom I know that I ſhall obtain them. For it is he only that grants them, and I am he that have a Right to obtain them, being his Servant that call upon him alone.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Likewiſe <hi>Origen</hi> againſt <hi>Celſus,</hi> the eighth Book ſaith, <hi>Above all things, we muſt pray to none but God and his only Son. Ignatius</hi> who lived near the time of the Apoſtles, ſaith in the Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle to the <hi>Philadelphians, You Virgins have none but Jeſus Chriſt, and the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Jeſus Chriſt in your Prayers. Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens Alexandrinus</hi> ſpeaks thus,<note place="margin">Cl. Ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xand. l. <hi>11.</hi> Strom.</note> 
                  <hi>There being none but one only that is truly good, which is God, both we and the Angels pray to him alone.</hi> And ſo <hi>Athanaſius. It is manifeſt</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that the Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arch</hi> Jacob <hi>in his Prayer joyned none with God, but him that is his Word;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Athan. Orat. <hi>4.</hi> cont. Arian.</note> 
                  <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is he only, that manifeſteth the Father unto us.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By a notorious Falſhood, among the Works of this Father, was foiſted a Book of the Mother of God, where ſhe is called the Queen of Heaven, and Chriſtians are commanded to adore her. But <hi>Bellarmine</hi> in his Book
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:100925:38"/>of Eccleſiaſtical Writers, and <hi>Banoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> in the year 48. § 19 <hi>&amp;</hi> 20. ack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowledges the Book to be ſuppoſititi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. By the like Forgery in St. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin</hi>'s Book of the Spirit and the Soul, there is a Prayer to the Saints inſert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but in the ſame Book <hi>Boetius</hi> is quoted, who was not born when <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi> dyed, an evident Proof that the book is falſely attributed to him.</p>
               <p>There is a Book of the ſame Father, <hi>Of the Care that muſt be had of the Dead,</hi> which is truly his, but corrupted and falſified in many places: For he is made to ſpeak of Prayers to Saints departed as good and laudable; yet he ſaith there, that the departed Saints know nothing of all that the Living do; and that if it were otherwiſe, his good and holy Mother would not have forſaken him. Then he addeth, <hi>The Spirits of the deceaſed are in a place where they ſee nothing of all that is done, or that happeneth to men in this Life.</hi> And a little after. <hi>It muſt be acknowledged that the dead know not that which is done here, while it is a doing, but they know it afterwards by them that dye and come to them.</hi> Was St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſo much overſeen
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:100925:38"/>as to teach that thoſe muſt be called upon by us who underſtand us not, nor know what is done here below, unleſs ſome dye, and perhaps after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards bring them News of it?</p>
               <p>This Advantage we have in this point, that our Adverſaries acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, that there is no Commandment of God for the Invocation of Saints, and that the Holy Scripture ſaith no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of it: And that under the Old Teſtament, that is, for the ſpace of four thouſand years, the Church uſed no Invocation of them. All the Prayers in Scripture are addreſſed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God alone, and therefore we have no Aſſurance or Encouragement to call upon the Saints, which we can ground upon the Word of God. Is it not enough for us to have the Son of God for our Interceſſor, who tells us, <hi>None comes to the Father but by me, John</hi> 14. For how can we pray with Faith and Aſſurance to thoſe who diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern not the Prayers of the Heart? For Scripture tells us that <hi>God alone knoweth the Hearts of men.</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 6.30.</p>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:100925:39"/>
               <p>I might ſay, that in the <hi>Roman</hi> Church many Saints are prayed to that never were in the World, and others whoſe Holineſs is very dubious, and whoſe Lives were very bad. Three hundred and ſeventy years paſt in the Chriſtian Church without any Invo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of Saints. The firſt that uſed it was <hi>Gregory Nazianzen,</hi> who yet in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocating the Souls of <hi>Conſtantius,</hi> (who was an <hi>Arian</hi>) of <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> and of <hi>Baſil,</hi> added this Clauſe, <hi>If thou un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand me,</hi> and <hi>If the Dead have any Senſe:</hi> But the Invocation of Saints was not received till a long time after in the Publick Service.</p>
               <p>All theſe things conſidered, My Lord, I cannot wonder enough that Your Grace chooſeth rather to be ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by one Paſſage of St. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> which perhaps is forged, than by the Word of God, and the Church of the firſt Ages after Chriſt. For would you ſubſcribe to all that St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſaith? In the firſt book of Virgins he ſaith, that <hi>the Angels fell by lying with Women.</hi> In his Speech upon <hi>Gratian</hi> and <hi>Valentinian,</hi> and upon the firſt Pſalm, he ſaith, that <hi>ſome riſe again
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:100925:39"/>ſooner than others.</hi> And in his Oration of the Faith of Reſurrection, he makes three ſorts of Reſurrection; the firſt of the Patriarchs and Apoſtles, the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond of the Gentiles converted to the Faith, the third of thoſe that come from the South and the North. In his firſt Book of Offices <hi>chap.</hi> 50. he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demneth ſecond Marriages. In the firſt Book of the Holy Ghoſt, he teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that the Baptiſm in the name of the Holy Ghoſt alone, without na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming the Father and the Son, is valid. In the tenth Sermon upon the 118 <hi>Pſalm,</hi> he ſaith that the Damned which are in Hell, ſhall in the end be ſaved, when the time of their Puniſhment is fulfilled.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Roman</hi> Church believeth not with <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> that all Saints ſhall be burnt with the material Fire of the day of Judgment, as we ſhall ſee here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after. Neither doth the <hi>Roman</hi> Church believe with <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> that <hi>Melchiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deck</hi> was Jeſus Chriſt himſelf. Many Pages might be filled with the like Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours of this Father, whoſe Authority you value more than that of God ſpeaking in the Holy Scriptures.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:100925:40"/>
               <head>Of Prayer for the Dead, and of Purgatory.</head>
               <p>Your Grace endeth your Allegati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Fathers with <hi>Theodoret</hi> and <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin.</hi> The firſt of which is alledged to ſay, <hi>We believe that there is a Fire of Purgatory, in which Souls are purged like Gold in the Furnace.</hi> The other ſaith, <hi>He that will not till his Field, ſhall be chaſtiſed in this World, and after his Death ſhall be puniſht in the Fire of Hell, or in that of Purgatory.</hi> And addeth, that he hath made a whole Book of the Prayers for the Dead, and that the whole Antiquity hath ſo pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cticed it.</p>
               <p>They that have helped you with theſe Paſſages have miſerably abuſed your Grace. It is true, that all the ancient Church prayed for the Dead, but in a manner which the <hi>Roman</hi> Church condemneth, and holds to be ridiculous and erroneous. Not one Paſſage can be found in the genuine Works of any Father, by which it can appear, that he prayed for the Dead, to draw them out of Purgatory.
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:100925:40"/>Could Your Grace have the Patience to. read St. <hi>Auſtins</hi> Book of the Care to be taken of the Dead, you would find that there is not one Word of Purgatory in the whole Book.</p>
               <p>The Chriſtian Church in the III and IV Ages after Chriſt, prayed for the Saints, for the Apoſtles, and Martyrs. The publick Form of thoſe Prayers is found in the eighth Book of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolick Conſtitutions of <hi>Clement,</hi> in the eighteenth Chapter. <hi>We offer un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee for all the Faithful which have been pleaſing unto thee from the Beginning of the World, Patriarchs, Prophets, Righteous, Apoſtles, Martyrs, Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors.</hi> The ſame is to be found in the Book of Eccleſiaſtick Hierarchy, that goes under the name of <hi>Dionyſius;</hi> and in <hi>Epiphanius,</hi> where he treateth of the Hereſie of <hi>Arius.</hi> All conſent, that none can imagine that theſe Prayers for the Saints, were to draw them out of Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory.</p>
               <p>St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> who writ in the Begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the fifth Century, was the firſt that ſaid it was doing Injury to a Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr to pray for him.</p>
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:100925:41"/>
               <p>It further appears, that the ancient Church had not belief of this Doctrine, in that they prayed for the Souls that ſlept peaceably; which Prayer to this day remains in the <hi>Roman</hi> Maſs, in which the Prieſt prayeth for the dead in theſe Words; <hi>Remember Lord thy Servants and Handmaids which are gone before us with the Sign of Faith, and which are ſleeping in a quiet Sleep.</hi> It is evident, That this Prayer was made in a time when the Belief of Purgato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry was not yet received, for thoſe that are burning (perhaps for many Ages) in a Fire ſeven times hotter than Hell, do not ſleep with a quiet Sleep.</p>
               <p>If you ask me why they pray'd for the dead, whom they held not to be in any Torment, it will be no hard Matter to give you Satisfaction. Firſt they asked that the Dead Perſon for whom they pray'd might riſe again to Salvation in the laſt day. Such was the Prayer of <hi>Judas Maccabaeus,</hi> 2 <hi>Mac.</hi> 12.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>v.</hi> 43 <hi>&amp;</hi> 44.</note> 
                  <hi>Doing therein</hi> (ſaith the Author) <hi>very well and honeſtly, in that he was mindful of the Reſurrection. For if he had not hoped that they that were ſlain
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:100925:41"/>ſhould have riſen again, it had been ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluous and vain to pray for the Dead.</hi> By the Judgment of that Author, the Prayer made for the dead in the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Church, is ſuperfluous and vain, ſince it is not made for their Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. That this was in old time the intent of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church when they pray'd for the Dead, it appeareth by the Prayers which are uſed ſtill in the Maſs for the Dead, of which theſe are the Words; <hi>We beſeech thee Lord to abſolve the Souls of thy Servants from all Bonds of Sin, that in the Glory of the Reſurrection, being riſen again, they may breath among the elected Saints.</hi> Thus <hi>Ambroſe</hi> prayeth for the Soul of <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doſius,</hi> and yet he ſaith, that he is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived into Chriſt's Tabernacles in the heavenly <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> And St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> prayeth for the Soul of his Mother <hi>Monica,</hi> which is among the Saints, and whom St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> believes to be enjoying heavenly Bleſſedneſs.</p>
               <p>Another Opinion was rife among the Antients, That ſome Souls ſhould riſe ſooner than other Souls, and that many Sins were to be expiated by the Delay of the Reſurrection. <hi>Tertulli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi>
                  <pb n="76" facs="tcp:100925:42"/>towards the end of his Book of the Soul, makes the Suffering of Souls after Death, even for the leaſt Sins to conſiſt in that Delay. In the Book of <hi>Monogamy, chap.</hi> 10. he will have a Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow to pray for her deceaſed Huſband, and that ſhe may keep him Company in the firſt Reſurrection. The like Prayer <hi>Ambroſe</hi> maketh for <hi>Gratian</hi> and <hi>Valen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinian, I beſeech thee O Supreme God, that thou wilt raiſe up again, more early, theſe moſt beloved young men.</hi> Here is then a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond end, for which the Ancients pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for the dead.</p>
               <p>They had one end more. It was an Opinion generally held by the Fathers, that in the day of Judgment, after men are riſen again they ſhall not enter into Paradiſe before they have been ſindged and purged by the Fire of the day of Judgment, ſome more, ſome leſs, as they have more or leſs ſinned. This is the Purgatory Fire of the Antients, of which their Books are full. Through that fire they make all the Saints to paſs, even the Virgin <hi>Mary. Lactantius lib.</hi> 7. <hi>cap.</hi> 21. declares thus his Opinion, which was then the general, <hi>When God hath judged the Juſt, he will try them by fire, and
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:100925:42"/>thoſe whoſe Sins are very conſiderable ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Weight or number, ſhall be ſindged and lightly burnt by the Fire.</hi> Thus <hi>Hil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lary</hi> upon St. <hi>Matthew,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hilar. <hi>in</hi> Mat. <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non.</hi> 2.</note> 
                  <hi>To them that are baptized with Holy Ghoſt, it remains yet to be perfected by the fire of Judgment.</hi> And in the part <hi>Gimel</hi> upon the 119 Pſalm, <hi>This Purification is reſerved for us after the Baptiſm of Water, which muſt ſanctifie us by the coming of the Holy Ghoſt, and refine us by the Fire of Judgment?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Again, <hi>Do we wiſh for the day of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in which we muſt paſs through that unwearied Fire, and undergo thoſe grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous Pains, to expiate the Soul of her Sins?</hi> And he makes the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> go through that Fire, <hi>If</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>even that Virgin which hath conceived God muſt undergo the Severity of that Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, who will dare to deſire to be judged by God?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> alſo ſaith, that all the Prophets and Apoſtles muſt in that day be purged by that Fire. In the 20 Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon upon the 118 <hi>Pſal. All muſt paſs through the Flames, even</hi> John <hi>the Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſt, whom the Lord loved, even</hi> Peter. And upon the 36 <hi>Pſal. The Sons of</hi> Levi <hi>ſhall be purged by Fire,</hi> Ezekiel, Daniel,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:100925:43"/>
                  <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Obſerve that he ſaith, <hi>they ſhall be;</hi> whence it appears, that he ſpeaks of a Fire which is not yet. St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs for it in the 16 Book of the City of God, <hi>chap.</hi> 24. <hi>By this Fire is under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood the day of Judgment, which ſhall ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate the Carnal, ſome to be ſaved by the Fire, ſome to be condemned to the Fire.</hi> And in the 25 Chap. of the 20 Book, <hi>By that which was ſaid it ſeems to be evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, that in that Judgment there will be ſome Purgatory Pains;</hi> And the Title of the chapter ſaith expreſly, that he ſpeaks of the Fire of the laſt Judgment. After the Purgation by that Fire, he holds that the Sentence of the laſt Judgment ſhall be pronounced, in the 21 Book <hi>chap.</hi> 16.</p>
               <p>Of that Purgation by Fire ſpeak <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naeus, Baſil, Gregory Nazianzen, Gregory Nyſſen,</hi> and <hi>Hierom.</hi> It is of that Fire, My Lord, that <hi>Theodoret</hi> and <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſpeak in the places which you alledge. And it is one of the grounds, why the Ancients prayed for the dead. For that St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> believed that Souls going out of the Body, went ſtreight either into Paradiſe or into Hell, and that there is no middle or third place call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:100925:43"/>Purgatory: it is clear by theſe Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages, in the 18 Sermon of the words of the Apoſtle, <hi>There are two Habitations, the one of the eternal Kingdom, the other of the eternal Fire.</hi> And in the 232 Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, which is againſt Drunkenneſs. <hi>Let none deceive himſelf, my Brethren, for there are two places and no third. He that hath not merited with Chriſt, ſhall periſh without doubt with the Devil.</hi> And in the firſt Book of the merit of Sins and of Pardon, <hi>ch.</hi> 28. <hi>There is no middle place, ſo that he that dwelleth not with Chriſt, can be any where elſe than with the Devil.</hi> The fifth Book of the <hi>Hypognoſticks</hi> ſpeaks thus, <hi>The Catholick Faith ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon Divine Authority, is, that the firſt place is the Kingdom of Heaven, and the ſecond is Hell. We believe no third place, and find none in the holy Scriptures.</hi> In the Book of the Vanity of the World, chap. 1. <hi>Know ye that when the Soul ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates from the Body, it is at the ſame In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant placed in Paradiſe for its good Works, or caſt down into the Gulf of Hell for its Sins.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I could bring Your Grace Paſſages by hundreds out of the Fathers, which expreſs that the Souls of the godly are
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:100925:44"/>preſently after Death carried into Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe or into Hell. I will content my ſelf with one or two.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cyprian</hi> in the Book againſt <hi>Demetri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> ſpeaks thus, <hi>This temporal Life being ended, we are ſequeſtred either in the Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation of Death, or in that of eternal Life.</hi> And in the ſame place, <hi>When men are gone from hence, there is no place left for Penitence, no Fruit, no effect of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, and in Death it ſelf they paſs to Immortality.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Fathers were ſo far from belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving that Souls were burnt in Purgato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, that many of them believed not that the Souls could be tormented without the Bodies. Thus <hi>Tertullian</hi> in the 48 Chap. of his Apologetick, <hi>The Soul</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>cannot ſuffer without ſolid Matter, that is, without Fleſh</hi> And <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory</hi> in the Oration of the Lords Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, <hi>The Fire can never work up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſeparate Soul, and Darkneſs cannot be grievous to it, becauſe it hath no Eyes. Ambroſe</hi> in the firſt book of Penitence Chap. 17. <hi>The Soul without the Body, and the Body without the Soul, cannot be Partakers of Puniſhment or Reward.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:100925:44"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> in the 39 Homily upon the firſt Epiſtle to the <hi>Corinthians. The Soul without the Fleſh ſhall not receive her hiden Goods, as likewiſe ſhe ſhall not be puniſht without the Fleſh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Truth is ſo ſtrong on our ſide, that many of our Adverſaries freely confeſs that the Fathers ſpeak little or not at all of Purgatory. <hi>Navarrus</hi> the Popes Penitentiary, in the beginning of the year of <hi>Jubile,</hi> ſaith, <hi>No Orthodox doubteth that there is a Purgatory. Yet the Ancients make no mention of it, or very ſeldom,</hi> and that he ſaith after <hi>Roffenſis,</hi> otherwiſe the Cardinal of <hi>Rocheſter,</hi> whom he alledgeth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Alphonſus de Caſtro</hi> one of the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors of the Councel of <hi>Trent,</hi> in his eight Book againſt Hereſies, upon the Word <hi>Indulgentia,</hi> ſpeaks thus. <hi>In the ancient Writers, the mention of the Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation of the Body of Chriſt is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry rare, of the Proceſſion of the Holy Ghoſt more rare yet, of the Purgatory they make almoſt no mention at all, eſpecially the Greek Authors; as alſo to this day the Greeks have not believed Purgatory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>One may ſee in the Dialogues of <hi>Gregory</hi> the Firſt, That <hi>Satan</hi> in his
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:100925:45"/>time was brewing that Myſtery by Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions and Apparitions of Souls, ſome of which ſaid that they purged them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves at the Smoak of Baths, others in the Wind, others in Rivers; and this was already in the year of our Lord 595.</p>
               <p>But the Popes that came after, found out another kind of Purgatory wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully gainful, whereby they have heap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up to themſelves and their Clergy infinite Riches. For the Pope by Bulls and Indulgences fetcheth Souls out of Purgatory at the Suit of thoſe that will come to his Price to buy them, and particular Maſſes, whoſe number is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite, are bought very dear, and none of them is ſung with particular Appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation to beggers or thoſe that have given nothing.</p>
               <p>Yet they hold one Age to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empted from Purgatory, for (ſay they) when Jeſus Chriſt cometh to judge the World, then all that live in the World ſhall be exempted from that Torment. In the mean while, one may wonder that whilſt Jeſus Chriſt is interceding for the Souls that are burning in that Fire (for he intercedeth for all the faithful) thoſe
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:100925:45"/>Souls come not out by this Interceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but by the Popes Indulgence.</p>
               <p>By all that has been ſaid here, Your Grace may perceive how much you are miſtaken in the Fathers, and indeed, by your manner of alledging them, it is eaſie to ſee that you have not read them; but that ſome ignorant men fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh you with Paſſages, which have quite another Senſe than that which they put upon them. If forſaking what you know from the holy Scripture, which (as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith) is able to make us wiſe upon Salvation, you take thoſe things upon Truſt which others tell you out of the Fathers, and if you greedily embrace all that ſhall be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented unto you of this kind, you will find enough to help your Reſolution, not to be ſeparated neither in this World, nor in the other, from my La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, your Dutcheſs. You ſay that you would know the Grounds of her Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, whilſt her Grace did not trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble her ſelf to know the Grounds of yours.</p>
               <p>My Lord, how could that Thought come into your Mind, to believe Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory upon two or three Paſſages
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:100925:46"/>of Fathers diſtored from their right Senſe; and to ſhut your Eyes againſt all that the Word of God ſpeaks againſt it?<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Apoc.</hi> 14.13.</note> Out of that good Word you might have learned, that <hi>Bleſſed are they that dye in the Lord, that they reſt from their Labours, and that their Works follow them;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 57.1. <hi>&amp;</hi> 2.</note> that <hi>when the righteous dyeth he ſhall enter into Peace:</hi> that we muſt <hi>make to our ſelves Friends by Alms,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 16.9.</note> 
                  <hi>which when we fail, may recieve us into everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Habitations.</hi> That Jeſus Chriſt ſaid to the repenting Thief crucified with him,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 23.43.</note> 
                  <hi>This day thou ſhalt be with me in Paradiſe.</hi> And yet by the Doctrine of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, he had need of great Purgation.<note place="margin">1 <hi>John.</hi> 1.7.</note> 
                  <hi>That the Blood of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt the Son of God, cleanſeth us from all Sin.</hi> This is our true Purgatory, God who is all juſt and all good, would he take two Payments for the ſame Debt, when the firſt Payment which is the death of Chriſt is ſufficient? would he delight to torment his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren for many Ages in an internal fire, for Sins which he hath freely par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned, as we learn of St. <hi>Paul,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.32. <hi>Col.</hi> 2.13.</note> that <hi>God for Chriſts ſake hath forgiven us all our Treſpaſſes?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:100925:46"/>
               <p>Every Father that chaſtiſeth his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, unleſs he be altogether unnatural, doth it to make them better; but the <hi>Roman</hi> Church will have God to burn his Children, not to make them more righteous (for by their Doctrine they are perfectly righteous before they enter into Purgatory) but to content himſelf, and ſatisfie his Juſtice. Let them find if they can, one example in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of any Soul that was ſent to Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory.</p>
               <p>It is very conſiderable that in the Levitical Law there are Sacrifices pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed for all ſorts of Sin and Polluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, even of Leproſie and the touching of a dead body; but that law preſcribes no Sacrifice for the dead, nor any Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice for their Relief, yea,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 26.12, <hi>&amp;</hi> 14.</note> it oppoſeth it plainly; for he that brought unto the Temple or Sanctuary his firſt Fruits, Tithes and Offerings, to give Thanks unto God for his Income, and all the Crop of the Year, was commanded to proteſt that he <hi>had not taken away ought thereof for any unclean uſe, nor given ought thereof for the dead.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>All theſe things, My Lord, drawn out of the Word of God, any founded
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:100925:47"/>upon the Nature of the Goſpel, which the Son of God hath brought you from Heaven, are they not better than ſome Paſſages of the Fathers, which you alledge contrary to their Intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and which ſay things that the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Church approveth not.</p>
               <p>How comes it to paſs, My Lord, that ſince your Marriage you have ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken another Rule for your Religion than the Word of God? You will be guided by the Fathers; but the Fathers ſend you back to the Scripture, and will not have you to reſt upon their Authority, acknowledging that they themſelves are ſubject to Errour. And for ſuch the <hi>Roman</hi> Church doth ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge them, and in a thouſand things find fault with them. Certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Holy Scripture without the help of mens Gloſſes hath light enough of its own to lead us to Salvation.</p>
               <p>O! My Lord, it is dangerous to dal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with God, and to bow the rule of his Word to the Will of another. As for My Lady Ducheſs your wife, I won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der not, that being nurſed in that Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaſion that her Religion is good, ſhe doth her utmoſt to draw you to it,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:100925:47"/>thinking thereby to do Service to God. Having no Inſtruction in the Word of God, her Grace doth that which ſhe thinks to be good; and I hope that God finally will be merciful to her. But you, My Lord, who have been care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully inſtructed in the Word of God, in whoſe Family God had planted his Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, whom God hath bleſt with ſo many effects of his Aſſiſtance, cannot but have a dreadful Account to give unto God.</p>
               <p>I could alledge ti Your Grace the memory of my Lord your Father, whom God had endowed with an incompara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Capacity; the Sorrow of your La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Mother, whoſe Death you haſten by your Change; the Anguiſh of your neareſt Relations, and of all your Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants and Subjects, whom you fill with Confuſion; and the Inconvenience to your Affairs, which you do your ſelf ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge. I chooſe rather to exhort your Grace in the name of God, and as your moſt humble and faithful Servant, that you take pitty of your own Soul; and that at leaſt you delay the taking of that final Reſolution, till your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn unto this your Town, and till I may endeavour to ſhew to thoſe Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:100925:48"/>in your Preſence, that they abuſe your Grace with thoſe Paſſages of the Fathers, wherewith they have armed you. But I am ſure they dare not appear before me to maintain thoſe things which they infuſe into your mind. You have been many years hark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to them alone, without ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any of our Counſel or Aſſiſtance. Grant us at leaſt, that we may have ſome days to anſwer them.</p>
               <p>I make no Doubt, but that by ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thus, I may looſe both your Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and your Ladies Favour. But ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving but few days to live, I commit to God all that may come of it, and will endeavour to diſcharge my duty with a good Conſcience. Which I will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways do without any Diminution of the Reſpect and Obedience which I owe to your Grace, and without inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting my continual prayers to God for Your Grace, and for my Lady Dutcheſs, as being,</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>My Lord,</salute> 
                  <signed>Your Graces moſt humble and moſt obedient Servant. <hi>PETER DU MOULIN.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
               <pb facs="tcp:100925:48"/>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
